Hello there, Charles, and how you up to things with? Yeah, we
are today's דף *daf* is צדי בית *tsadi bet* 92. We have
finished up some we were in the middle of some אגדתא agadata.
*aggadata* about יעקב Yaakov, *Yaakov*. We are finishing it up about how
יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* had to free the angel so that the angel
could go and praise God, which was his one chance in his
lifetime or in a long time. And now we pick up at
the very end of צדי אלף עמוד בית *tsadi aleph amud bet*.
והאיכא ברוך ברוך *v'ha-ika baruch baruch*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had
said that ישראל Yisrael *Israel* is better than the angels because ישראל
Yisrael *Israel* gets to say God's name in praising God, actually it
was an interesting comparison talking about the שמע *Shma* as a type
of a praise of God which is not normally how we understand
it. Anyway, after two words, שמע ישראל השם *Shma Yisrael Hashem*, and
the angels only after three words, קדוש קדוש קדוש *Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh*,
which is the vision, you know, in ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* about how the
angels say קדוש קדוש קדוש *Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh*. The point is, is
that what do they follow קדוש קדוש קדוש *Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh* with?
ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד *Baruch shem kevod malchuto le'olam va'ed*.
And there, wait, that's us too. ברוך שם *Baruch shem*, excuse me,
ברוך כבוד השם ממקומו *Baruch kevod Hashem mimkomo*. So that's after two
words. So how do you mean the angels only say it after
three words? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says ברוך אופנים הוא דאמרי
ליה *Baruch ophanim hu de-amri lei*. No, that's not the normal מלאכים
*malachim*, that's the אופנים *ophanim* which are the heavenly whatever
literally wheels or something, but anyway it's part of the vision there
of what goes on in the heaven and they're at a higher
level. But the normal מלאכים *malachim* only get to say it after
three words.
We're at a higher level?
Apparently. There's a whole big תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* and מהרש"א *Maharsha* if
you want to look at that.
They're better than the מלאכים *malachim* and not the אופנים *ophanim*?
Exactly. We're equal to the אופנים *ophanim*. אי בעית אימא *I ba'it
eima*, and if you want what?
Yes, see these are in the פסוקים psukim *psukim* about מלאכים *malachim*
and the אופנים *ophanim*, etc. אי בעית אימא *I ba'it eima*, if
you want, here's another answer for those that are bothered by this
hierarchy or by thinking that the אופנים *ophanim* are equal to us.
כיון דיהיב רשותא יהיב *kivan de-ye-haiv reshut ye-haiv*. Once you started with
קדוש קדוש קדוש *Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh* and once the angels have the
permission to say God's name, then they were given license to say
it only after two words or maybe even without any preference, but
they in order to preface... thank you, but in order to first
say God's name, they needed three קדוש קדוש *Kadosh Kadosh* acknowledgments of
God's holiness as opposed to ישראל *Israel*, which is of course ironic
and that's the point the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is making, that you
would think the angels who are quite aware of God's holiness, you
know, the permission to say God's name, you know, to invoke the
name of God, would come easier because they're more aware of it.
And that is the point that, you know, ישראל *Israel* is greater.
ישראל *Israel* is greater because in some ways saying that ישראל *Israel*
is more aware of God's holiness, maybe because they, you know, sort
of see the way God, God, you know, present is, is expressed
in the actual world, so that gives them a sense of awareness
that the angels doesn't have, you know, or is the idea that,
you know, that ישראל *Israel* somehow is called by the name of
God in a way that the angels aren't, you know, it's not
exactly clear, but obviously there's a certain, you know, irony here, which
is exactly the point that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is making, or
just that the, or just that ישראל *Israel* is given in a
certain degree more license. You know, maybe it's not that they're more
able to perceive than the angels, but maybe somehow God wants to
give them the opportunity to connect to God in a way that
is not necessary for the angels. So there's a lot of speculating
you could do about this, but obviously the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is
very much intending that, that irony, yes.
I was going to say it's just interesting that, you know, the
one example which at least occurs to me is like the prime
example phrase, and not talked about: שירו להשם כי גאה גאה *Shiru
l'Hashem ki gao ga-a*, right? We didn't bring אז ישיר *Az Yashir*
to represent singing השם *Hashem's* name at that point, you know. Yeah,
but that's you're not praising God, you are expressing
your intent to praise that I will praise God. I mean, I
guess you could sort of say that means I am, exactly, I
am praising God. But you're also not saying something about God. You're
not saying God is holy, you're not saying God is blessed, you're
saying that, you know, I praise. You're expressing more your action than
directly saying something about God. So there's a subtle difference there between
the actual phrase. But we do this after ברוך
אתה השם *Baruch ata Hashem*.
But that's an interesting point. Yeah, I guess looking at פסוקים psukim,
*psukim*, but yeah, go ahead.
Does it express anything about the fact that we have free will
and the angels don't?
Well, I was sort of alluding to that as well, but, but
how that ties into the blessing is not exactly clear, but that's
sort of what I was saying that we were, God wanted to
give us more license because given the ability to sort of, the
need to connect to God in a way that the angels, you
know, don't. But yeah, obviously that's always the question to ask in
terms of angels versus people about the degree of holiness versus free
will, struggle and so on. Okay, now we go on.
וישר *Vayasar*, now we're going back to פסוקים psukim *psukim* about יעקב
Yaakov. *Yaakov*. וישר אל מלאך ויוכל
*Vayasar el malach vayuchal*, so this is a little poetic recap of
the story of יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* in הושע Hoshea, *Hoshea*. He strove
with the angel and he was victorious or he was able. בכה
ויתחנן לו Bacha vayitchanen lo, *bacha vayitchanen lo*, he cried and he
supplicated to him. So it's not exactly clear who the players are.
איני יודע מי נעשה שר sar, למי *eni yodea mi nasa sar
l'mi*. When it says... and by וישראל כי שרית, Sarita so he
says in this recap in הושע, Hoshea, it's not exactly clear who's
doing what. You have to know the back story in order to
understand this because like all of the what do you call it?
Antecedents of the pronouns are ambiguous. So it says I don't know
who became a master over who, who, you know, who was supreme.
כשהוא אומר Keshuomer when the verse actually in בראשית Bereishit says כי
שרית עם אלוהים, Ki sarita im Elokim, you, יעקב, Yaakov, strove with
angels, struggled with angels or gods, whatever that אלוהים Elokim means. הוי
אומר, Hevi omer, יעקב נעשה שר על המלאך. Yaakov naasa sar al
hamalach. יעקב was the one who became a שר, sar? a you
know a what's the word for שר? A prince over the angels,
meaning he became he was the one that was victorious. בכה ויתחנן
לו, lamed-vav. he cried and supplicated to him. איני יודע מי בכה
למי. Eni yodea mi bacha lemi. From the פסוק pasuk in הושע,
Hoshea it's not clear who is crying and who is supplicating. כשהוא
אומר Keshuomer when the verse says ויאמר שלחני, Vayomer shalcheni, send me
free. הוי אומר, Hevi omer, from this I understand that obviously who's
in the who is in the position that is that is begging?
So הוי אומר, Hevi omer, that makes it clear wherever we מלאך
בכה ליעקב, Malach bacha leYaakov, the angel cried to יעקב. Okay. So
anyway, it's really not saying too much new, it's just saying that
the פסוקים in הושע are not clear on their own. They're nice
poetic retelling, but you need to know the back story in order
to know what's going on. All right, כי שרית עם אלוהים ועם
אנשים. Ki sarita im Elokim ve'im anashim. Now we're going to interpret
that פסוק. pasuk. You have striven or you have been victorious over
angels, let's say, and people. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רמז רמז לו,
Remez remez lo, the angel hinted to יעקב שעתידים שני שרים לצאת
ממנו, She'atidim shne sarim latzet mimenu, that he will have two future
you know great authorities coming out of יעקב, princes. ממנו ראש גולה
שבבבל, Mimenu rosh golah shebeBavel, the head of the exile in בבל,
Bavel, ונשיא שבארץ ישראל, veNasi shebeEretz Yisrael,
and the נשיא, Nasi, right, the exilarch, in the land of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. מכאן רמז לו גלות, Mikan remez lo galut, and
from here was the hint to exile because he indicated that you
will need two authorities, an authority in בבל Bavel and an authority
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now where is it from? That שרית
is the sense of prince and authority, and שרית עם אלוהים Sarita
im Elokim means you will have a prince not among אלוהים. Elokim.
What does אלוהים Elokim mean here? So read the rabbinic way, אלוהים
Elokim is judges and a court that has authority to to execute,
you know, capital punishments and other types of you know, the authorities
of the court are referred to in the תורה, Torah, you know,
when it comes to bringing a matter before court, it says אל
האלוהים יבוא דבר שניהם. el haElokim yavo devar shneihem.
So the נשיא שבארץ ישראל, Nasi shebeEretz Yisrael, the exilarch in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, is the one that also has rabbinic authority and
the authority of the courts. So that is שרית עם אלוהים. Sarita
im Elokim. You'll have an officer, a prince, among אלוהים, Elokim, and
you will also be עם אנשים, im anashim, and in a normal
secular authority. If you want to say a little more simply without
the whole אלוהים Elokim bit, a religious authority and a secular authority.
Is the you know, the רבי רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rebbi Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi, the exilarch in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the land of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, was both a political and religious authority,
whereas ראש גולה שבבבל, Rosh golah shebeBavel, you know, here often about
the ריש גלותא, Resh Galuta, the head of the the head of
the exile, but he was often what was going on in his
household was not so up-and-up in terms of הלכה. halacha. So he
was a he was a secular, not a religious authority. So you
will have both of these you know, descendants who have positions of
authority. Yes.
And so some of the anti-Zionists object to the idea we shouldn't
have a Jewish government unless it's religious, but we have that example.
Right. What can I tell you? And we have the example from
most of the בית שני, Bayit Sheni, but people people like living
in a romantic non-realistic past. Okay. So moving on. Okay, ובגפן שלושה
שריגים. Uvagefen shlosha sarigim. Now we are
in once we're interpreting things, we're interpreting other visions or the first
interpretation at least ties into the previous one, but then we're going
to digress a little. So this is the vision about the about
the wine steward of פרעה, Paroh, who told his dream to יוסף,
Yosef, and on the vine there were three branches.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
amar Rav, אלו ג' שרי גאים, Elu gimel sarei ge'im, שריגים sarigim
sounds like שרי גאים, sarei ge'im, haughty princes, or princes of you
know, power,
היוצאים מישראל בכל דור ודור, hayotzim miYisrael bechol dor vador, that come
out of the Jewish people in every generation. What does that mean?
Well, let's first finish this.
פעמים ששניים כאן ואחד בארץ ישראל, Pe'amim sheshnayim kan ve'echad beEretz Yisrael,
sometimes there are two here in בבל Bavel and one in the
land of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. פעמים ששניים בארץ ישראל ואחד כאן,
Pe'amim sheshnayim beEretz Yisrael ve'echad kan, sometimes there are two in the
land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and one here. So what he
means is people that are really like you know, very wealthy, people
that are so sometimes there are personages of great influence and wealth
or whatever, so that's שלושה שריגים שרי גאים, shlosha sarigim sarei ge'im,
like haughty, but haughty in the sense of not necessarily arrogant, but
like just of great power and influence.
Accepted by the people?
I mean, like
that's not the point here. So anyway, yeah, sometimes there are two
here, one in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, sometimes the reverse. יהבו רבנן עינייהו ברבנא עוקבא
וברבנא נחמיה בני ברתיה דרב. Yahavu rabanan einaihu beRabana Ukva uveRabana Nechemya
benei barta d'Rav. the sons of Rav's daughter, so apparently they were
wealthy people, so maybe it was also maybe it was also around
the time of Rosh Hashanah Yom Kippur with the Yom Kippur appeal
so he was giving this דרשה drasha hint hint and everybody was
looking at them. Okay. And we could use a new בית המקדש.
Base Hamikdash. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava said אלו שלשה שרי
גויים. eilu shelosha sarei goyim. Now that we're doing this דרשה drasha
about שרי גויים, sarei goyim, obviously the tie-in was here and in
Israel and people of influence, now we're going to do a דרשה
drasha about this whole about the vine. So שריגים, sarigim, שרי גויים.
sarei goyim. So רבא אמר אלו שלשה שרי גויים, Rava amar eilu
shelosha sarei goyim, three princes of the nations,
non-Jewish people of great influence, שמלמדים זכות על ישראל בכל דור ודור,
she-melamdin zechut al Yisrael be-chol dor va-dor,
that teach merit over the Jewish people in every generation. So what
does that mean? So
רש"י Rashi says שרי גויים מלאכים, sarei goyim malachim, that there are
angels, angels of the other nations that learn merit over the Jewish
people. It's not necessarily true. You could have read it to see
that an acknowledgment that although
often the Jewish people were beset with enemies from the outside world,
there were sometimes friends of the Jews who would sometimes try to
come to their defense. So maybe it's an acknowledgment of that. But
רש"י Rashi says we're talking about heavenly angels.
Okay. תניא, Tanya, we learned in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, maybe רש"י'ס Rashi's influenced
also by the phrase מלמדים זכות, melamdin zechut, which often has to
do with sort of arguing the case in front of God. Then
it would also be particularly ironic that it's the angels of the
non-Jews that are defending the Jews in front of God. תניא רבי
אליעזר אומר, Tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, גפן
זה העולם, Gefen zeh ha-olam, the גפן Gefen refers to the world.
שלשה שריגים זה אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Shelosha sarigim zeh Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov.
Okay, three obviously you're going to turn to אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham
Yitzchak ve-Yaakov. והיא כפורחת עלתה נצה, ve-hi ke-forachat alta nitzah, it was
like sporting sprouting forth its bud came out, אלו האמהות, eilu ha-imahos,
those are the mothers.
הבשילו אשכלותיה ענבים, hivshilu eshkeloteiha anavim, its clusters became ripe of grapes,
אלו השבטים, eilu ha-shevatim, those are the tribes. So that was the
vision. It was the אבות, אמהות, avos imahos the tribes, the things
that are the fruit, the beautiful fruit that comes forth out of
the world. אמר לו רבי יהושע, Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua, so said
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua back to him, וכי מראים לאדם מה שהיה?
ve-chi marim le-adam mah she-hayah? What would be the point of having
a vision of the אבות avos, אמהות imahos, and the tribes? Those
are already around in the time of יוסף. Yosef. So why would
God show this dream? And it's also true that the dream wasn't
to יוסף, Yosef, it was to the wine steward, but I guess
the point being that it was supposed to be heard by יוסף.
Yosef. So what would be the point of something that was just
a fact that was already on the ground? דלא אומרים לאדם אלא
מה שעתיד להיות. de-lo omerim le-adam ela mah she-atid li-heyos. The point
is to show somebody something that has not yet occurred. אלא גפן
זה תורה, Ela Gefen zeh Torah, the גפן Gefen refers not just
to the world, but specifically to תורה. Torah. שלשה שריגים אלו משה
אהרן ומרים, Shelosha sarigim eilu Moshe Aharon u-Miriam, משה אהרן ומרים, Moshe
Aharon u-Miriam, which is interesting to see that, מרים Miriam sprouting forth
from the vine of תורה. Torah. The use of the word תורה
Torah here is going to be a little bit strange as we'll
see, whether it maybe specifically really just means sort of world of
the Jews. Let's keep on reading. והיא כפורחת עלתה נצה, ve-hi ke-forachat
alta nitzah, it blossomed forth, אלו סנהדרין. eilu Sanhedrin. This is the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. What that has to do with תורה, Torah, I mean
obviously סנהדרין Sanhedrin imposes the law, but anyway, and also specifically the
idea of the sprouting forth and the blossoming is not so clear.
הבשילו אשכלותיה ענבים, hivshilu eshkeloteiha anavim, it had the cluster of grapes
ripened, אלו הצדיקים שבכל דור ודור, eilu ha-tzaddikim she-be-chol dor va-dor, the
righteous. So again, that's very strange, right? The other imagery made more
sense. The אבות avos and the אמהות imahos give birth to the
children. Right here,
it's like תורה, Torah, משה אהרן ומרים, Moshe Aharon u-Miriam, סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
צדיקים. tzaddikim. It's not exactly a group that necessarily goes together, other
than that they're all wonderful Jews, but you know, it's not exactly
clear. The תורה Torah doesn't seem to be the theme exactly unless
תורה Torah is meant in a broad sense about like living an
ideal religious life, so it includes צדיקים, tzaddikim, but then what's the
role of the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? And how does סנהדרין Sanhedrin give birth
to the צדיקים? tzaddikim? So I don't get it. המהרש"א ha-Maharsha did
not discuss it. I didn't see if there's any other commentary. Anything
in there? I don't know. Did Rabbi Schorr say anything in terms
of that? Not really. Okay. All right. Okay, so moving on. Okay,
so that actually seems to anyway be רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's problem
with it. אמר רבן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Gamliel, said רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel back, עדיין צריכים אנו למודעי. adayin tzerichim anu la-Modai. We still
need a מודעי, Modai, which is a phrase that might be referring
to a particular person, but it also
means somebody who knows how to explain אגדתא. Agaddata. You know, we
need a yeah, רבי אליעזר המודעי, Rabbi Eliezer HaModai, exactly. So it
was referring to אליעזר המודעי Eliezer HaModai specifically, but it was also
a phrase... which means like, oh, we could really use אליעזר המודעי,
Eliezer HaModa'i, or we could really use somebody here that knows how
to do a good דרש drash on the פסוקים, because this is
not satisfying. All right. Why? דמוקי לה כולה בחד מקום Demuki lah
kulei bechad makom because we're going to have Rabbi Eliezer HaModa'i exactly
quoted in a minute. דמוקי לה כולה בחד מקום Demuki lah kulei
bechad makom that he says it's all talking about one location. Now
he actually means geographically one location, but the point could also be
what we just said before, that there's like one consistent theme going
on here. Right. I'm sorry, here it does quote directly Rabbi Eliezer
HaModa'i. רבי אליעזר המודעי אומר, Rabbi Eliezer HaModa'i omer, right. So you're
right, I'd have to check, but you're right, אדיין אנו צריכין למודעי
adayin anu tzrichin leModa'i normally is a lead-in to directly quoting Rabbi
Eliezer HaModa'i, but clearly acknowledging his authority or ability to interpret אגדתא.
Agaddata, רבי אליעזר המודעי אומר, Rabbi Eliezer HaModa'i omer, גפן זו ירושלים,
gefen zu Yerushalayim, that's Jerusalem. שלשה שריגים זה מקדש מלך וכהן גדול.
shlosha sarigim ze mikdash melech vechohen gadol. Things at least were in
Jerusalem, so maybe there's not exactly the same theme, right? The temple,
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, those go together. The king, king is
not exactly the same, but at least they're all in ירושלים Yerushalayim
and it's all sort of the center of both religious and political
authority. Okay. והיא כפורחת עלתה נצה. vehi cheforachat alta nitza. What is
the blossoming? אלו פרחי כהונה. elu pirchei kehuna. So that's a sort
of rabbinic phrase, the פרחי כהונה, pirchei kehuna, the young כהנים, kohanim,
like לפרוח lifroach to blossom, refers to young כהנים. kohanim. So פורחת
porachat is they're making that connection. Okay, fine. But that's כהנים kohanim
working in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so we still have that
focus on ירושלים Yerushalayim as the center.
הבשילו אשכלותיה ענבים, hivshilu eshkeloteha anavim, it blossomed for clusters of grapes,
אלו נסכים. elu nesachim. That is the wine offering. You have a
direct connection with grapes, right, and squeezing out the grapes and getting
the wine, and you bring the wine in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, which does seem a little bit like okay, it's all in
the same place, but still loses a little bit of the punch,
right, because you're talking about like these people that you know all
the activity around serving God and the people that sort of you
know the center of that and talking about one particular קרבן, korban,
you know, if you wanted like emphasize the greatness of the נסכים
nesachim then fine, but then you wouldn't be discussing the מלך melech
here. So again, it's a little funny these themes are not exactly
as consistent as we would like them.
And Joseph showed him the
word,
yeah,
that's also not explained, like since when is this relevant to the
dream of the steward and why does Yosef have to hear about
this? You know, it could just be that maybe the Gemara is
bothered like why such detail about a dream that really, you know,
has no lasting relevance for us? I mean, even though it was
necessary for the story there, you know, why all of this particular
detail? Let's find a way in which this dream is also telling
us something about the Jewish people.
What about the baker's dream?
Yeah, that it does not get to that. Yeah, I don't know,
I agree with you, it's not clear to me why the Gemara's
so focused on interpreting this and also that the interpretation doesn't seem
so satisfying, which at least the Gemara acknowledged before. But even this
interpretation seems to be you know like you don't get the punch
of it. Okay. רבי יהושע בן לוי מוקי לה במתנות.
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
muki lah bamatnot. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says it's talking about gifts.
We'll see what it means, like gifts of the Jewish people, or
gifts, a gift to God, I should say. דאמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי גפן זו תורה. de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi gefen zu Torah.
I'm sorry, no, as I just said, gifts God gave to the
Jewish people. So the גפן gefen is the תורה, Torah, the vine,
like you know, it gives elixir of life and so
on. שלשה שריגים זה באר עמוד ענן ומן. shlosha sarigim ze be'er
amud anan uman. Those are the gifts that they had in the
desert, right, in the wilderness: the well of water, the עמוד ענן,
amud anan, the pillar of cloud, and the מן. man. והיא כפורחת,
vehi cheforachat, it's sprouting forth, עלתה נצה, alta nitza, it blossomed, אלו
הביכורים. elu habikkurim. So the idea of blossoming forth is the ביכורים.
bikkurim. Now ביכורים bikkurim is a gift we give God. So Rashi
says yes, what it means is God gives us first fruits so
that we can then give the first fruit to God, but it's
meaning God gives us also first fruits. אלו ביכורים. elu bikkurim. הבשילו
אשכלותיה ענבים, hivshilu eshkeloteha anavim, it had clusters of grapes, אלו נסכים.
elu nesachim. So again, that's again something what we're giving God, but
maybe it means again God gives us grapes so we give God
back the נסכים. nesachim. So it refers to the sense of sort
of these blessings that are coming you know from the earth and
are then given back to God. So at least there anyway there's
a similar type of an imagery if you want, right, that here's
this thing sprouts forth, you squeeze it, and it was given to
Pharaoh. So there at least there's a nicer sort of parallel in
the sense of God gives you all these blessings, right, and then
you sort of return them to God. So there at least there
is some sort of a parallel. By the way, I don't know
if how I can fix this in with the עמוד ענן amud
anan except maybe with Sukkot, but even the באר be'er and the
מן man have a way of being given back to God. The
באר be'er there's a song in the Torah: באר חפרוה שרים, be'er
chafaruha sarim, עלי באר ענו לה, ali be'er enu lah, right, and
the מן man is put in a צנצנת, tzintzenet, in a container,
right, by the ארון. aron. So the only thing is the עמוד
ענן, amud anan, I don't exactly get. But of course according to
one opinion the עמוד ענן amud anan is what we recognize and
acknowledge on Sukkot is זכר zecher for the עמוד ענן. amud anan.
So maybe it works for all of them and then it you
know then it has a sense God has given to us. and
we acknowledge it back and does somewhat more parallel the story. Okay.
רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, אמר *Rabbi Yirmiyah bar
Abba amar*, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmyah בר אבא *Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba*
says, גפן אלו ישראל *Gefen elu Yisrael*, the Jewish people, וכן הוא
אומר V'chein hu omer גפן ממצרים תסיע *vechen hu omer Gefen miMitzrayim
tasi'a*, a vine from Egypt you will sort of take away, remove,
lift up. So therefore the Jews were taken out of מצרים Mitzrayim
*Mitzrayim*. שלשה שריגים *Shlosha srigim*, the three branches, אלו שלשה רגלים *elu
shlosha regalim*, there's another three, שישראל עולין בהם בכל שנה ושנה *sheYisrael
olin bahem bechol shanah vashanah*. Okay, so maybe to acknowledge since the
theme of the שלשה רגלים *shlosha regalim* is the ex- is the
Exodus, right? Obviously פסח *Pesach*, but סוכות *Sukkot* as well is part
of that story. שבועות *Shavuot* does not fit so much, but okay
anyway. But okay, certainly you know the sort of the connection of
what happened with the whole Exodus story, and שבועות *Shavuot* certainly the
way חזל Chazal *Chazal* understand it in terms of מתן תורה Torah,
*Matan Torah* is all part of that. So that connects, that's the
three רגלים *regalim*. והיא כפורחת עלתה נצה *Vehia keforachat altah nitzah*, it
blossomed forth, הגיע זמנם של ישראל לפרות ולרבות *higia zmanam shel Yisrael
lifrot velirbot*, the time for the Jewish people had come to be
fruitful and multiply when they were taken out of Egypt. וכן הוא
אומר V'chein hu omer *Vechen hu omer*, ויז נצחם על בגדי וכל
מלבושי אגאלתי *vayeiz nitzcham al bgadai vechol malbushai ego'alti*. Did I skip
a line? וכן הוא אומר *Vechen hu omer*, בני יוסף Yosef פרו
וישרצו *b'nei Yosef paru vayishretzu*. Okay. So now it's a little funny
going back and forth, right? We speak about we're going to take
the we're speaking about the three רגלים *regalim*, but now we're going
back to the fact that they have yet to come out of
מצרים *Mitzrayim*. They were fruitful and they multiplied, but it was time
to remove them. בני יוסף פרו וישרצו *B'nei Yosef paru vayishretzu*, עלתה
נצה *altah nitzah*, the blossom had risen up, הגיע זמנם של ישראל
להיגאל *higian zmanam shel Yisrael lehiga'el*, now that they had been fruitful
and multiply, now it was time to blossom forth, it was time
for them to be redeemed. וכן הוא אומר *Vechen hu omer*, and
so the verse says, I skipped my place again, וכן הוא אומר
ויז נצחם על בגדי וכל מלבושי אגאלתי *vechen hu omer vayeiz nitzcham
al bgadai vechol malbushai ego'alti*. And I just read it a second
ago. Yeah, did we? It could be I wasn't paying attention.
It's the, this verse, yes?
No? Okay. מי זה בא מאדום חמוץ בגדים *Mi
zeh ba me'Edom chamutz bgadim*, right?
Right, right. Okay fine. I was a little bit distracted during that,
I must admit. Anyway. Okay. Okay, so anyway, so this is talking
about the splattering of their blood is on my, you know, is
on my, is on my clothes. And all of my, you know,
and all of my, and all of my cloaks I have, have
become sort of disgusting with the blood, meaning the blood of the
Egyptians. So that's tied into the idea of the sprouting forth, עלתה
נצה *altah nitzah*, the נצחם *nitzcham* is the word connecting it.
Oh, redemption from Egypt? Oh yeah, that's a, you know, a נבואה
*nevuah* for later.
Yeah, but I think here, right, no I think here it's very
specifically about Egypt. Okay.
Okay. הבשילו אשכלותיה ענבים *Hishilu anotav havin*, הגיע זמנם של מצרים *higia
zmanam shel Mitzrayim*, there you go, the time for Egypt had come,
לשתות את כוס התרעילה *lishtot et kos hatareilah*, to drink the the
cup of poison. So now we're getting into very sort of sense
of like, you know, not just redemption but the redemption at the
expense of killing and punishing the Egyptians. והיינו דאמר רבא *Vehaynu d'amar
Rava*, this is what Rava says, שלשה כוסות האמורים במצרים *shlosha cosot
ha'amurim beMitzrayim*. So now we understand by the way, and you do
also get the tie-in, because at least first of all there's a
tie-in to Egypt, it's a dream about Pharaoh. And Pharaoh is drinking
wine. So now this wine of drinking Pharaoh is drinking the cup
of, you know, of punishment, of poison of punishment, of whatever, so
that which is a, which is an imagery, right? I will make
them drink this, you know, that's a imagery in תנך *Tanakh*. And
therefore it's looking towards the time where Israel will come out and
the Egyptians will drink the cup of punishment. All right, so והיינו
דאמר רבא *vehaynu d'amar Rava* and that's what Rava says, שלשה כוסות
האמורים במצרים *shlosha cosot ha'amurim beMitzrayim*, the three cups that are said
in Egypt, meaning in this dream of the wine steward, it says
three times כוס פרעה Paroh היה בידי *kos Paroh hayah beyadi*, את
הכוס *et hakos*, את הכוס *et hakos*, so it says כוס *kos*
three times. What is that? למה *Lamah*? Why? אחד כוס ששתה בימי
משה *Echad kos sheshatah bimei Moshe*,
one is the cup of punishment that they drank, you know, that
they drank at the time of Moshe, at the Exodus, when the
Egyptians were punished. ואחד ששתה בימי פרעה נכה *Veechad sheshatah bimei Paroh
Necho*, one is the time of פרעה נכה *Paroh Necho* when נבוכדנצר
*Nevuchadnetzar* comes, you know, and he's conquering the world. So he also,
you know, conquers Egypt and פרעה נכה *Paroh Necho* suffers as a
result and his people are wiped out. ואחד שעתיד לשתות עם כל
עובדי כוכבים *Veechad she'atid lishtot im kol ovdei chochavim*, and one that
they're going to single them out more than the other nations, everything
because they've already got their punishment for, you know, for subjugating the
Jews, but that they will get punished when all the nations are
punished in the future time and everybody else, you know, gets their
comeuppance, so the Egyptians will as well. Okay, so this here again,
this is a way that פסוקים *Pesukim*, rather than just randomly associ-
I shouldn't say randomly, but rather than seemingly somewhat arbitrarily associating it
to different things, there's a sense almost of a little bit of
a narrative and a sense of connection to the idea of Pharaoh
drinking. So before there was a sense of, you know, we got
gifts from God and like the same way
that About blossoming as a sense of redemption and something new and
new life and the whole idea of פסח as the spring, so
that whole sense of the blossoming is the time of redemption. And
then פרעה drinks the cup of wine, which means that the Egyptians
suffer their punishment.
Okay, where are we? Now we are,
where was I? Okay. אמר ליה רב אבא לרבי ירמיה בר אבא,
Amar leh Rav Abba leh Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, so רב אבא
Rav Abba said to רבי ירמיה בר אבא, sounds like his son,
כי דרש ליה רב להני קראי באגדתא, ki darshei leh Rav leh
hanei krei b'Agaddata, when רב Rav interpreted these פסוקים in אגדתא, Aggadata
where was I, כי דרש ליה באגדתא כוותך דרשה ליה, ki darshei
leh b'Agaddata k'voseich darshei leh,
he interpreted it just like you interpreted it. Right, and his interpretation
was the whole thing here of, you know, about the time for
redemption and מצרים suffering their punishment. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, now רבי שמעון לקיש Rabbi Shimon Lakish said,
אומה זו כגפן נמשלה, Uma zu k'gefen nimshala,
this nation is like a vine, like we just said before in
the earlier דרשה. drasha. זמורות שבה אלו בעלי בתים, Zemoros she'ba elu
ba'alei battim,
but now we're going to turn a little bit away from the
exact vision of יוסף's dream and just talk about the image of
ישראל as a vine. So the branches are the בעלי בתים, ba'alei
battim, which often in the גמרא Gemara here has the sense of
not just homeowners, but people of wealth and of means. So the
people that give branches are sort of the strong branches, the people
that due to their means manage to support the Jewish people. So
they're what? Stalwarts, yeah, maybe, but also
specifically here about money. Okay, so those are the בעלי בתים. ba'alei
battim.
Where were we? אשכולותיה, Eshkoloseha, אשכולות שבה אלו תלמידי חכמים, eshkolos she'ba
elu talmidei chachamim, because obviously the clusters of the grapes are the
purpose of it is to produce תורה, Torah and so that is
the תורה Torah sages. עלים שבה אלו עמי הארץ, Alim she'ba elu
amei ha'aretz, how about the leaves,
those are the people of the land. Now עם הארץ am ha'aretz
here does not have, very often has a negative connotation, here it
does not seem to be, it means sort of the people that
work the land. The farmers and so on and
the people that do the normal trades and so on, so the
same way the purpose of leaves is to protect the clusters, so
the people that do all of the non-religious activities and they work
and they farm and they do the trades and so on, they
actually give sustenance and allow both the
תורה Torah sages to blossom forth. So those are the עמי הארץ.
amei ha'aretz.
And קנוקנות שבה, knoknos she'ba, the קנוקנות, knoknos, which seems to be
these just the either the protrusions, the tiny little branches but that
don't actually bear any fruit, and don't seem to have any real
purpose, אלו ריקנים שבישראל. elu reikanim she'b'Yisrael. Those are the empty people,
those are the people that don't contribute too much to the nation.
They're not תורה Torah scholars, they're not producers, they're just hanging around
doing nothing.
Okay, so that's the part of the vine that doesn't seem to
be that purposeful. דהיינו דשלחו מתם, De'hainu d'shalchu m'tam, that's what they
sent from over there from ישראל the following message: לבעי רחמי
אתכלא על עליא, Liba'ei rachamei itkala al ilaya, the clusters should pray
for the leaves, דאימלא עליא לא מתקיימי אתכליא, de'imallei alaya lo miskaymei
itkalya, were it not for the
leaves the clusters would not survive. So the תורה Torah sages have
to really acknowledge, and it's not just the wealthy people that write
the big checks, it is the leaves, everybody that does all the
other things in society that need to get done
in order that you can survive. The way that sort of the
רמב"ם Rambam has a, I mean, it could be also so there
is obviously still on the one hand there's a sense of gratitude
and acknowledgment, but on the other hand there's still a sense of
elitism. Now of course that's not to
be a surprise from the point of the גמרא, Gemara that the
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are at the top of the hierarchy, but
it comes through a real, like I'm thinking of the רמב"ם Rambam
in מורה, Moreh, is it in the מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim he
says this? Somewhere he says this, he basically sort of follows the
idea, I mean he's a little bit sort of more the Greek
idea, that the whole world is only created for the purpose of
the philosophers who
can contemplate ultimate truths. So he says, so if that's true, why
are so many of the people in the world not philosophers? He
says well, in order for the philosophers to have their clothes and
to get their food and to get their wheat, how many people
have to go into planting wheat and harvesting it and grinding it
and turning it into bread, and raising sheep and shearing it and
turning it into cloth and turning it into food? So you need
everybody else in the world so that the philosophers can sit and
spend their time philosophizing. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara sort of say,
it's not being that extreme but it is
in the subtler way talking about, obviously, it's normal understanding that the
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are the true fruit, but at the same
time with a real acknowledgment about how. their success depends on everybody
else doing, you know, doing what's necessary to settle the world and
to create a productive society. Okay. So that is, that is a
digression on the digression about this whole dream about the vine. Now
we go back, now we're wrapping up a little אגדתא Aggadetah. before
we go back. Okay. ואכרה לי בחמשה עשר כסף V'achra li b'chamisha
asar kasef
and I either dug for me or purchased for me with 15
כסף. kasef.
So what does this mean? So this is a digression because it's
about again the righteous who are those that for the sake of
which the people survive. So it's again here talking about the grapes,
and you know, the purpose is to produce the grapes, but the
grapes are dependent on the leaves. So here we're going to talk
as well about sort of the righteous and the way people are
dependent on the righteous. So the verse says I purchased for me
whatever in 15 talents of silver or pieces of silver. אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yozadak אין כירה אלא לשון מכירה. ein kirah ela lashon mechira.
Kirah means to sell or to purchase, שנאמר shene'emar בקברי אשר כריתי
לי bekivri asher karisi li
the grave that I had purchased for me. Again, it could mean
I dug for me, but חז"ל are understanding it means I purchased
for me. So בחמשה עשר, bachamishah asar, 15, זה ט"ו בניסן, Zeh
tet-vav beNisan, again
tying into the theme of redemption, this is the 15th of Nisan
שבו נגאלו ישראל ממצרים. shebo nigalu Yisrael miMitzrayim. So I purchased the
Jewish people for me on the 15th, on the 15th of Nisan,
כסף, kasef, with כסף, kasef, what's כסף? kasef? אלו צדיקים, eilu tzaddikim,
these are the righteous. וכן הוא אומר and so the verse says
צרור הכסף לקח בידו. Tzror hakesef lakach beyado.
The bundle of silver he took in his hand. This is a
whole משל mashal in משלי Mishlei about the Jewish people warring after
the other gods and leaving God, and they say oh don't worry
about God, He left the house, like He's the husband, He left
the house and He took all of His money, He's not coming
back for a while. And the משל mashal here is, you know,
He took the צדיקים tzaddikim with Him, so we can go ahead
and do what we want.
So anyway, one minute. Okay.
So the meaning here is that I redeemed the Jewish people because
of the חמשה עשר כסף, chamishah asar kasef, because of the 15
righteous. I redeemed the Jewish people on the 15th, on Pesach, because
of the כסף, kasef, because of the righteous people. וכן הוא אומר
חמר שעורים ולתך שעורים, chomer se'orim v'letech se'orim,
that's the end of the verse.
A חמר chomer of barley and a לתך letech of barley. A
חמר chomer is 30 סאה, se'ah, a לתך letech is 15 סאה,
se'ah, so the total is 45 סאה. se'ah. So what does that
mean? אלו מ"ה צדיקים שהעולם מתקיים בהם, Eilu mem-hei tzaddikim sheha'olam mitkayem
bahem, this is the 45 righteous people that the world survives in
their merit. I heard of the ל"ו. lamed-vav I know, so there
are other גמרות Gemaras that it's the ל"ו which is the one
that has more captured our imagination about the ל"ו צדיקים. lamed-vav tzaddikim.
Easier to do.
But this גמרא Gemara is 45 צדיקים. tzaddikim. Okay, ואיני יודע אם
שלשים כאן וט"ו בארץ ישראל. v'eini yodeia im sheloshim kan v'tet-vav b'Eretz
Yisrael. This is also a nice bookend to the beginning of the
גמרא, Gemara, right, about a division between Israel and בבל. Bavel. I
don't know if there are 30 in בבל Bavel and 15 in
Israel. Remember there also was a two and one, a two to
one ratio about wealthy people. So here's a two to one ratio
about צדיקים. tzaddikim. So I don't know if the 30 are here
and the 15 in Israel,
or 30 in Israel and 15 here. כשהוא אומר, K'shehu omer, when
the verse says ואקחה שלשים הכסף, v'ekcha sheloshim hakesef, I took the
30 pieces of silver ואשליך אתו בית ה' v'ashlich oto beit Hashem
and I cast it in the house of God אל היוצר, el
hayotzer, to the
whatever,
to the treasure house, הוי אומר שלשים בארץ ישראל, hevei omer sheloshim
b'Eretz Yisrael, so that's talking about the house of God and it's
the 30 and that is talking about the 30 righteous are in
the land of Israel, וט"ו כאן, v'tet-vav kan, and there are 15
here.
Which is a land that was been really poor.
What? Yeah, I don't, what?
No, wasn't there like... עניותא aniyuta was where, was supposed to be
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
בבל? Bavel? It's in contradistinction to the עניה, aniya, which is maybe...
Maybe, that's true. Okay, so anyway, so this is a bookend to
the thing before about where the wealthy people are, a two to
one ratio. Here too there is a two to one ratio, but
interesting, the בבלי Bavli is acknowledging that there are more righteous people
in Israel than in בבל. Bavel.
And here it's also the tie-in is to the theme of redemption
that we've been talking about, and the Jewish people are redeemed. Why
are they redeemed? They're redeemed here for the sake of the righteous,
which also a little bit ties into the idea before about the
importance of the תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim. Here it's not righteous and
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim are not the same, but again the importance
of like these sort of religious people of the nation. Yes, and
they're smarter.
Because they're צדיקים? tzaddikim?
No, the other place as well.
Right, אוירא דארץ ישראל מחכים. Avira d'Eretz Yisrael machkim. Right,
that's true. Although if you were to like line up all the
גמרות, Gemaras, you know, they would not exactly be I think a
consistent message that came out. Okay, so now let's take a look.
אמר אביי Amar Abaye ורובייהו משתכחי בבי כנישתא דתותי אפסא. v'rubaiyu mishtach'chi
b'vei knishta d'Tuti Afsa. Most of the righteous here in בבל Bavel
can be found in the synagogue of תותי אפסא. Tuti Afsa. Now,
תותי אפסא Tuti Afsa might have been the name, רש"י Rashi says
אפסא Afsa is a יציאה, yetzia, like
a... An apse. What's an apse? Oh.
It's like a little, it's like a little alcove. I don't know.
Okay. Okay. So most of them can be found in that synagogue
over there. All right, so it's good they knew where their צדיקים
Tzaddikim were. והיינו דכתיב Vahainu dechtiv and this is what's
meant, ואמר אליהם, Va'omar aleihem, thank you, אם טוב בעיניכם הבו שכרי
ואם לא חדלו וישקלו את שכרי שלשים כסף. Im tov be'eineichem havu
schari ve'im lo chadalu vayishklu et schari sheloshim kasef. And I said
to them, if it is good in your eyes,
then give me my fee, and if not, cease, and they paid
out for me 30 pieces of silver. Now that's a whole vision
in זכריה Zechariah about, which we don't have to get into here,
but anyway, which is a vision about
the punishment that will come to the other nations, and he's being
paid as a shepherd which represents God is removing His protection from
the other nations and so on. So here it seems to be
that give me back my 30 righteous people and God sort of
takes the righteous, which are now not among the other nations, although
it's strange because we said these 30 righteous were in Israel, not
in the land of Israel, not in בבל, Bavel, but somehow because
God is taking back His 30 righteous people, or they're not among
the other nations, therefore the other nations are now exposed to punishment.
Seems to be the point here, although I have to admit I
don't really get it because the 30 righteous we said were in
the land of Israel, not in בבל. Bavel. And רש"י Rashi on
the I didn't really get either. רש"י Rashi says החזירו לי את
הצדיקים שאתם מקבלים עליהם שכר. Hechziru li et hatzaddikim sheatem mikablim aleihem
schar. Give me back the צדיקים Tzaddikim for the sake of, or
who's he talking to? Is he talking to the Jewish people? Give
me back my צדיקים? Tzaddikim? I don't get it. And רש"י Rashi
says the next רש"י Rashi ולקחתי שלשים כסף ונתנו אותם צדיקים לדורות
ישראל. Velakachti sheloshim kasef venitnu otam tzaddikim ledorot Yisrael. They were established
now that they would be in the in Israel. So it's saying
that originally there were these righteous amongst the nations, and God is
saying give me those righteous people back and now I'm not going
to have them with you, you're now going to be exposed to
punishment, and now I'm going to put them in the Jewish people.
That sort of seems to be how רש"י Rashi is reading it.
Okay. And the גמרא Gemara now continues, רבי יהודה אומר אלו שלשים
צדיקי אומות העולם שאומות העולם מתקיימים עליהם. Rabbi Yehuda omer elu sheloshim
tzaddikei umot ha'olam sheumot ha'olam mitkaymim aleihem. But now, of course, now
you have them still amongst the non-Jews. These are the 30 righteous
people amongst the non-Jews, amongst the nations of the world, that for
their sake the nations of the world survive. עולא אומר אלו שלשים
מצוות שקבלו עליהם בני נח ואין מקיימים אלא שלשה. Ulla omer elu
sheloshim mitzvot shekiblu aleihem bnei Noach ve'ein mikaymim ela shelosha. These are
the 30 מצוות mitzvot that the בני נח bnei Noach took upon
themselves, but they only keep three of them. Now
what are the 30? If you look at רש"י, Rashi, שלשים מצוות
לא נפרשו ומהכא הוא דקיילא. Sheloshim mitzvot lo nifrashu umeihacha hu dekayla.
I never know what those 30 מצוות mitzvot are, there's no other
גמרא Gemara about it, but this גמרא Gemara understands that they had
30 מצוות, mitzvot, not seven. But they only keep three of them,
אלא שלשה. ela shelosha. אחת, achas, what are the three they keep?
So now it's not what we would think, right? The what we
know is the seven מצוות. mitzvot. Now that it's 30, it's got
to be a lot more that we're not normally familiar with. So
אחת שאין כותבים כתובה לזכרים. achas she'ein kotvim ketubah lezecharim. That even
though, right? Right exactly, the whole debate around the around
legalizing gay marriage, there's a couple of גמרות Gemaras that actually speak
in addition to the prohibition of homosexuality in the תורה Torah. or
male homosexual behavior, there's a גמרא Gemara that specifically speaks about מעשה
מצרים Ma'aseh Mitzrayim which is, right, which is when it's sort of
writing the כתובה ketubah for both female and male homosexual marriages, which
means the institution of marriage beyond the question about male homosexual sex.
So for those that are more liberal in terms of issues of
gay marriage, these are גמרות Gemaras that need to be contended with.
So here the one מצווה mitzvah that they do is in addition
forget the question about homosexual sex, that they might do, but at
least they don't have an institution of marriage. ואחת שאין שוקלים בשר
המת במקולין. ve'achas she'ein shoklim besar hameis bemakkolin. The other is that
they don't weigh out the dead corpses, they don't sell the meat
of dead corpses, of human corpses. ואחת שמכבדין את התורה. ve'achas shemechabdin
et haTorah.
At least say recognize honor the תורה. Torah What does that mean?
They honor the Jewish people? Does that mean that the influence of
the תורה Torah, through Christianity made its way into, you know, into
the larger society? Not exactly clear. Anyway, three that we've never heard
of before because if you're going to go from 7 to 30,
you're going to have to add a couple. So, thus to finish
this point, so the point is it starts by saying because of
these righteous, 45 righteous, you know, that's sort of why Israel has
been redeemed and is protected. Then based on this verse it speaks
about taking the righteous. So it seems to be saying, oh, there
were the righteous among the nations, they have somehow been removed. Although
the idea of being removed was not clear at the end because
the first statement was there are 30 righteous among the nations. And
then it says, oh no, there were 30 מצוות, mitzvot, and that
actually they don't do, they only are doing three of them. So
again, that maybe they had these things of merit, but now they
don't really have them so much, which was the vision in זכריה,
Zechariah, something is the protection is being removed. That is the whole
vision there in זכריה, Zechariah, and now they are sort of exposed
to punishment. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, regarding the same-sex marriage, the archaeologists have never found any evidence
of the Egyptians doing that.
Some evidence from
Rome.
No, the
point of that was somehow that the 30 way רש"י Rashi understood
which ties into the next line of גמרא, Gemara. that the 30
rights there were 30 righteous among the nations and they were removed
from the nations and they were put in the Jewish among the
Jewish people.
The word though, the thing that disturbs me is the word threw
it, that
sounds right.
Yeah, disturbed. Right, right, we did not really discuss that. I don't
have much to say.
Yes, Bobby. I have a question about appearances versus reality. Specifically when
he says that at least they keep three, but you could also
read it that the three that they keep are just appearances.
That's an interesting point, so they don't actually keep it.
Right, right. And then the thing in the תורה, Torah as an
anti-Semitic practice, it's very nice that they read the Bible, but you
know...
Yeah, oh that's a very nice point, very unexpected.
Also there's these
humble people that sit in the... I hear in the commentary that
the אופסא Apsa is the place where the people that's not the
miserable people.
Aha, right, yeah,
but that's the opposite you mean, you mean that they don't... Yeah
but it's appearances... it's the opposite, meaning they are the righteous people
but you wouldn't know it because of their appearances.
Oh that's a very nice take. I think I see a guest
post there. Okay anyway, but that's very nice. I don't know how
much further back that works, but it certainly works there at the
end with the idea of righteousness, like what is true righteousness as
opposed to surface righteousness. That's very nice, thank you. Okay, now we
get back to
אגדתא. I am not רבי אליעזר המודעי, Rabbi Eliezer Hamodai, so I
feel a little more comfortable here. דאין נוהג בעוף. De'ein Noheig Be'of.
Now the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh does not apply by birds. דהא
חזינן דאית ליה, De'ha Chazeinan De'is Lei, why not? We see birds
have the same type of a sinew or whatever nerve. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אית ליה ולא עגיל, Is Lei Ve'lo Agil, they
have it but it is not in a rounded part of the
thigh, and they don't have a rounded part of the thigh, and
we learn from the fact it says אשר על כף הירך Asher
al Kaf HaYerech that sort of the sphere, the כף, kaf, כף
kaf is like a cup, a not a cup, a ladle, right,
exactly, like a bowl, right. Oh I said it meant no the
flesh of the thigh, maybe? I think it meant from I said
it meant that it's like you know the fleshy part of the
thigh is curved the same way a spoon is curved. So birds
don't have that. So בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmyah, so רבי
ירמיה asks, אית ליה ולא עגיל, Is Lei Ve'lo Agil, אית ליה
בבהמה ולא עגיל, Is Lei Be'veheimah Ve'lo Agil, let's say you happen
to have a particular bird that has actually that type of a
rounded thigh? Or you have a particular type of a בהמה beheimah
that doesn't have the rounded thigh? מאי? Mai? What would be the
law? בתר דידיה אזלינן, Batar Didei Azlinan, do you go by the
particular animal in front of you and if it has a כף
הירך, Kaf HaYerech, therefore it's a problem? או בתר מיניה אזלינן, O
batar minei azlinan, do you go by the species? You would think
it should be obvious you go by the species, I mean since
when would the תורה Torah tell you look at each individual animal
just to see if its thigh happens to be rounded? But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara interestingly ends by תיקו, Teiku, we don't know, so
you'd have to be strict both ways. So if you found a
bird with a rounded thigh, you'd have to start applying the laws
of גיד הנשה. Gid HaNasheh. Okay, נוהג בשליל, Noheig Be'shalyil, now it
applies to a fetus, we're back to fetuses, can't get away from
them. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, וחלבו מותר, Ve'chelbo mutar, the fat, although
there's a debate in the משנה Mishnah whether גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh
applies to the fetus, everybody agrees that the fat is
permissible. מותר לדברי הכל. Mutar le'divrei hakol. So the גמרא Gemara says,
חלבו דמאי? Chelbo de'mai? Which fat? אילימא דשליל, Ileima de'shalyil, the fat
of a fetus, right, so the question is does a nine-month-old fetus
have its own status or
not? והא מיפלג פליגי ביה, Ve'ha miflag paligi beih, but they debate
this. The same way they debate whether you give it its own
status for to consider to have a גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, remember
the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
by the nine-month-old fetus, is it its own animal or not? So
the same way they debate גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, they'll debate the
fat. דתניא, De'tanya, we learned a ברייתא, Baraita, נוהג בשליל וחלבו אסור
דברי רבי מאיר, Noheig Be'shalyil ve'chelbo asur, divrei Rabbi Meir, it applies
by the שליל, shalyil, the גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, and the חלב
chelev is forbidden, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, that the
nine-month-old fetus has its own status even in the mother's womb and
it has a גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh and it has fat. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehudah omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says, אין נוהג
בשליל, Ein Noheig Be'shalyil, no the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh does not
apply, it's just a part of the mother, וחלבו מותר, Ve'chelbo mutar,
the fat is permissible. So you can't say they agree about the
fat, they say the whole debate is do you give this nine-month-old
fetus independent status or not? So as the same way they debate
about the גיד, gid, they debate about the
fat. Okay, so one minute, okay, ואמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא,
Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya, מחלוקת בנמצא חי, machlokes be'nimtza chai,
this is about a nine-month-old fetus, והלך רבי מאיר
לשיטתו ורבי יהודה לשיטתו. Ve'halach Rabbi Meir ve'shitato, Rabbi Yehudah ve'shitato. They
each go according to their reasoning, because if you remember way back
the debate was if you שחט shecht the mother and there's a
nine-month-old fetus, does the שחיטה shechitah on the mother work for the
fetus? If the fetus is less than nine months old or it's
dead, every... Everybody agrees it's part of the mother. But if it's
nine months old and viable, there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
an independent entity. So the same way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
that the שחיטה shechita of the mother does not work for the
fetus and it's an independent entity, he says that the גיד הנשה
Gid Hanasheh applies and the fat applies, it's its own animal. Whereas
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, it's just a part of the
mother, it's not its own animal, the שחיטה shechita works. And if
it's a part of the mother, then it doesn't have a גיד
gid and it doesn't have a חלב. cheilev. The only גיד gid
is the mother's גיד, gid, and the only חלב cheilev is the
mother's חלב. cheilev. So that's their debate. So you can't say they
agree about the fat of the fetus, because that is the same
debate. ואלא חלבו דגיד? Ve'ela chelbo de-gid? Ah, meaning, okay, forget the
whole issue about the fetus. Yes, there's a debate about the גיד
הנשה gid hanasheh of a fetus as it applies, forget the fetus.
Let's just talk about a גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. Is there a
problem with the fat surrounding the גיד הנשה? gid hanasheh? Is that
forbidden fat or not? Because we're going to see that there was
a debate between a different debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, whether the fat around a גיד הנשה, gid
hanasheh, forget fetuses, is forbidden or not. So here the statement is
that even though they debate about the גיד gid of a fetus,
they all agree that the fat around the גיד gid is permissible.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. I jumped
ahead to the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says: ואלא חלבו
דגיד? Ve'ela chelbo de-gid? You want to say the fat of the
גיד? gid? הא מיפליג פליגי בה. Ha-milat palig ba. But they debate
that. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: גיד הנשה, מחטט
אחריו בכל מקום שהוא. gid hanasheh mechateit achrav be-chol makom she-hu
You have to dig after it wherever it is. Meaning even where
the גיד, gid, if you remember that picture that we showed the
other day, what has all of those little branches that they and
they go off in much thin branches, so according to this position,
you have to dig after all of its sort of side branches
and dig it out wherever you'll find it. וחותך שמנו מעיקרו. Ve-choteich
shemano me-ikaro. And
you have to cut out the fat from the very root. דברי
רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
Notice by the way it says שמנו, shemano, because actually halakhically forbidden
fat is חלב, cheilev, halakhically permissible fat is שומן. shuman. So we're
actually going to see that the whole problem here the fat according
to everybody that most rabbinic. So therefore even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says you have to get rid of the fat refers to it
as שומן, shuman, not as חלב. cheilev. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says dig after it and remove the fat. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi
Yehuda omer: גוממו עם השופה. Gummo im ha-shofeh. No, you don't have
to dig it out, you just sort of cut out the major
the major גיד. gid. Now רש''י Rashi says it means the meaning
don't have to worry about the little branches and where it branches
forked, just cut out sort of the part that's exposed and right
there at the surface, the big big גיד gid and also presumably
cut out maybe some exposed fat, surface fat, but you don't have
to worry about the fat that's deeply inside that you have to
dig.
גוממו Gummimo means to like cut it off, עם השופה im ha-shofeh
I think means sort of like in the part that is sort
of exposed or at the surface. I don't know, how do they
translate it there in the English? You have an English there? Joe,
what do they say for
the גוממו עם
השופה?
gummo im ha-shofeh?
Levels it off on the surface of the rounded flesh. Okay, so
basically you just don't have to dig after it, גוממו gummo is
opposed to חותך, choteich, you don't have to dig after it, you
just cut off the thing that's at the surface,
and השופה ha-shofeh is like the surface or the rounded flesh. So
that both means according to this is combining really רש''י Rashi and
תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says the emphasis here is not to talk
about the fat, that he's actually ignoring the fat. He says the
fat is totally permissible, forget about the fat. And not only that,
you don't have to dig after the little places it branches off,
just cut off the part that's at the surface, the most exposed
part of the גיד. gid. That's what תוספות Tosafot says. And then
רש''י Rashi says it also means with maybe some surface fat, but
you don't have to dig after the fat. So there's even a
question whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is even mentioning the fat at
all. But he's certainly saying you don't have to dig after the
fat and even the גיד, gid, you don't have to dig after
the גיד, gid, you only have to worry about the part that
is right there at the exposed level. Okay, so that's their debate.
So you see that they do debate about the fat of the
גיד. gid. So the גמרא says: לעולם חלבו דגיד. L'olam chelbo de-gid.
No,
no, no, we are talking about the fat of the גיד. gid.
ומודה שמואל, U'modeh Shmuel, but what שמואל Shmuel is admitting is דמדרבנן
אסור. d'mederabbanan assur. That even though רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you
have to remove it, it's only rabbinic. And again notice that I
pointed out that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir uses the word שומן shuman
and not חלב. cheilev. So when שמואל Shmuel says everybody agrees about
the fat, he wasn't talking even about our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה
Mishnah is about the fetus, forget our משנה. Mishnah. What he's talking
about is when it comes to the fat of the גיד הנשה,
Gid hanasheh, there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
agree that at least biblically it's permissible. They have a rabbinic difference
whether there's a rabbinic problem, but biblically it's permissible. And that might
actually be what שמואל Shmuel is saying is the meaning of the
משנה, Mishnah, because the משנה Mishnah says, if you look at the
משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah says: ונוהג בשליא וחלבו מותר. Ve-noheig b'shilya
ve-chelbo muttar. So חלבו מותר, chelbo muttar, שמואל Shmuel might be saying
that doesn't mean we're moving on from the fetus. First there was
a question of does it apply to a fetus? That was a
debate רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The next line
says everybody agrees that the fat around the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh,
forget the fetus, is at least biblically permissible. Maybe there's a rabbinic
problem. So even if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's a problem,
at most it's rabbinic. Okay. דתניא de-tanya we taught in a ברייתא
braitah ושומנו מותר v'shumano mutar again notice the word שומן shuman and
not חלב chelev the fat is
permissible ישראל קדושים נהגו בו איסור Yisrael kedoshim nahagu bo issur but
the holy people of Israel they have they decided to separate themselves
from it and not eat it but technically it's permissible. מאי לאו
רבי מאיר mai lav Rebbi Meir here don't you see it's רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir and even according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir it's
just like a מנהג minhag not to eat it but really technically
it's permissible דאמר מותר מן התורה ואסור מדרבנן d'amar mutar min ha-Torah
v'asur mi-derabbanan and now we're sort of saying נהגו בו איסור nahagu
bo issur means rabbinic although not so clear. So it's biblically permissible
and it's rabbinically forbidden.
The גמרא says one minute
ממאי mi-mai how do you know that? דילמא רבי יהודה היא dilma
Rebbi Yehuda hi maybe this is רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda maybe רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying it's totally permissible and some people have
a practice not to eat it. אבל לרבי מאיר מדאורייתא נמי אסור
aval le-Rebbi Meir mi-d'oraita nami asur maybe רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would
say that it when he says it's forbidden and you have to
dig after it maybe he would say even biblically. So the גמרא
says no לא סלקא דעתך lo salka datchach that doesn't make sense
דתניא de-tanya we taught in a ברייתא braitah גיד הנשה gid hanasheh,
מחטט אחריו בכל מקום שהוא mechateit achara b'chol makom shehu. you have
to dig after wherever the גיד gid sort of spreads out even
the tiny little extensions of the גיד gid ושומנו מותר v'shumano mutar
and the שומן shuman again notice the word of the שומן shuman
ושומנו מותר v'shumano mutar is permissible. So מאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה
חיטוט man shamat lei d'it lei chitut who is the one that
said you have to dig after all the places that it branches
off to? רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir וקאמר ושומנו מותר v'ka-amar v'shumano mutar
its שומן shuman is permissible. Okay so now what you are seeing
is is that and that really seems to be what שמואל Shmuel
points as how to read the משנה. Mishna. When the משנה Mishna
says חלבו אסור chelevo asur don't read that about the fetus forget
about the fetus we're moving on. We're saying there's one debate about
the fetus what about the fat around the גיד gid halakhically that's
totally permissible. Ah don't we have a debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda where רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
you have to dig it out and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says
maybe only the surface or not at all? Fine that's a debate
about is it a rabbinic problem is it a מנהג minhag problem
but biblically it's totally permissible. Okay and now what actually the question
is even within רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir how do you read the
different positions of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
because now we're having רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir say ישראל קדושים נהגו
בו איסור. Yisrael kedoshim nahagu bo issur. So does that mean נהגו
בו איסור nahagu bo issur that we treat it as a מנהג
minhag or does it mean מדרבנן? mi-derabbanan? One phrase the גמרא uses
מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. How about רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that we don't hear
him say anything about it? Does he say it's nothing it's totally
permissible or does he say at least maybe it's there's a מנהג
minhag about it? So there's all these different questions. תוספות Tosafot is
inclined to think based on again I told you the earlier תוספות
Tosafos that he says you don't even have to cut away the
fat for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda even the surface fat that for
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda there's not even a מנהג minhag it's totally
permissible. Within רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir there's this ambiguity whether it's a
מנהג minhag or a מדרבנן mi-derabbanan but everybody agrees it's not biblically
problematic. Let's just read a little bit more moving on from the
שומן shuman to the actual גיד. gid.
Did anyone explain why?
Why it's this מנהג minhag developed? Yeah well that's a good question
and the question is is it developing because it's like חלב chelev
and it's a concern about its similar fat? It's hard to imagine
because it's calling it שומן shuman the whole time it seems because
it is connected to the גיד gid and if you're removing the
גיד gid you remove the stuff that's connected to the גיד gid
you remove all the fat that the גיד gid itself so it
seems to be an extension of not eating the גיד gid also
as we're about to see and we'll do just two sentences of
the whole question is there might not even be taste to the
גיד. gid. So it might almost feel like purposeless to throw out
a גיד gid that has no taste so you're also getting rid
of some of the stuff around it that actually is more food-like
and has more taste. Okay so that seems to be it. Let's
read that a little bit. אמר רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא
אמר רב Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta amar Rav לא
אסרה תורה אלא קנוקנות שבו. lo asra Torah ela knoknot she-bo. Remember
the קנוקנות knoknot from before? The תורה Torah only forbids the extended
part of the גיד gid though where it branches off because those
are parts that at least have a little bit of taste in
them. Wait but the גיד gid itself too? No not the גיד
gid itself. And not the fat? No no
for we're we're beyond the fat. עץ הוא eitz hu yes
it is like a piece of wood the גיד. gid. But nevertheless
ורחמנא חייביה ve-rachmana chayveih the תורה Torah obligated you for it. So
yes you are חייב chayav obviously for the main גיד gid and
maybe not for the branches. That was the רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda debate of the branches. So it's actually
quite ironic the first position that says because it doesn't have any
taste and because it's like a piece of wood it can't be
what the תורה Torah is referring to. אמר אביי Amar Abaye טבתי
דעולא מסתברא tavati d'Ulla mistabra it makes sense like עולא Ulla דאמר
רב ששת אמר רב אסי d'amar Rav Sheshet amar Rav Assi חוטין
שבהלב אסורין ואין חייבין עליהם. chutin she-ba-chelev asurin v'ein chayavin aleihem. If
you have forbidden fat and you have these little sort of you
know sinews going fat streams going through the fat those are
forbidden and you do not transgress why not if they're going through
the fat? אלמא חלב אמר רחמנא ולא חוטין. alma chelev omar rachmana
v'lo chutin.
Fat means fat it doesn't mean the strings going through the fat.
הכא נמי גיד אמר רחמנא hacha nami gid amar rachmana so if
the תורה Torah says גיד gid it means the גיד gid it
means the main sinew ולא קנוקנות v'lo knoknot and not the little
stuff that are going through it. So here you have a very
you know a very reasonable response which is I I understand you're
bothered about the fact that it doesn't have taste but the תורה
Torah says גיד gid it means גיד gid it doesn't mean the
stuff that branches off and just because it's the גיד gid doesn't
have taste you can't relocate the problem of the תורה to the
קנוקנות. knoknot. So we actually have the irony. That one says it
doesn't apply to the גיד gid only to the branches, but we
actually say the reverse, that it applies to the גיד gid and
perhaps doesn't apply to the branches at all. That was the whole
issue with רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda before
because they're not primary גיד. gid. And even though the גיד gid
has no taste, that primarily what it does apply to. There's another
debate later on that the גמרא already referred to whether גיד gid
has taste or not. תוספות tries to figure out how that debate
correlates to this debate. Obviously the position that is bothered by the
lack of taste of the main גיד gid and relocates the prohibition
feels that it's important that the גיד gid has taste. But if
you're of the position that a גיד gid doesn't have taste, you're
then you're more obviously comfortable to say that the גיד, gid, even
though it's like a piece of wood, is what is prohibited, not
the side branches.
Right. That's a good point. But anyway, to go back to the
משנה. Mishnah. But anyway, this question, one question is we know what
the גיד gid is, do we assume it has taste or not?
Here what's surprising is that if you assume that the גיד gid
needs to have taste, you might wind up relocating what you think
is actually prohibited as the גיד gid from the main גיד gid
to the side branches. Okay. Okay. Yeah, you
might go with the substitute teacher tomorrow. Please behave for him. He's
going to give a full report to me.